Nathan Appleton Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Nathan Appleton Papers 1850-1904 (bulk 1876-1902)
MSS57067
Appleton, Nathan, 1843-1906
400 items 4 containers 1.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Army officer and merchant. Correspondence, notes, autobiography, speeches and writings, clippings, printed matter, and miscellany relating primarily to Appleton's connection with Ferdinand de Lesseps and to his work as American agent for Compagnie universelle du canal interocéanique de Panama, a French company attempting to build a canal across Panama.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Appleton family.; Appleton, Nathan, 1843-1906.; Bacon, Edwin M. (Edwin Munroe), 1844-1916--Correspondence.; Belknap, George E. (George Eugene), 1832-1903--Correspondence.; Bellamy, Edward, 1850-1898--Correspondence.; Bergh, Henry, 1811-1888--Correspondence.; Cortelyou, George B. (George Bruce), 1862-1940--Correspondence.; Curtin, Andrew Gregg, 1817-1894--Correspondence.; Draper, John William, 1811-1882--Correspondence.; Forney, John W. (John Wien), 1817-1881--Correspondence.; Hanna, Marcus Alonzo, 1837-1904--Correspondence.; Hoar, George Frisbie, 1826-1904--Correspondence.; Lesseps, Ferdinand de, 1805-1894.; Long, John Davis, 1838-1915--Correspondence.; Norton, Charles Eliot, 1827-1908--Correspondence.; Spooner, John C. (John Coit), 1843-1919--Correspondence.; Whitney, Anne, 1821-1915--Correspondence.
Organizations
Compagnie universelle du canal interocéanique de Panama.; National Board of Trade (U.S.)
Subjects
Canals--Panama.; Free trade.; Tariff--United States.; Voyages and travels.
Places
Boston (Mass.)--Social life and customs.; Panama Canal (Panama)
Occupations
Army officers.; Merchants.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Nathan Appleton, army officer and merchant, were given to the Library of Congress in 1976 by his great-niece, Dorothy Weld Coxe.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Nathan Appleton are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1843, Feb. 2 Born, Boston, Mass.
1863 Graduated, Harvard College, Cambridge Mass. Commissioned junior second lieutenant of the Fifth Massachusetts Battery, Light Artillery, United States Volunteers
1864 Severely wounded in battle on the North Anna River in Virginia Resignation from army accepted; discharged for wounds
1864-1865 Visited Europe
1865 Became volunteer aide-de-camp to Brigadier General C. S. Wainwright, commander of the Artillery Brigade of the Fifth Army Corps Brevetted captain to rank for gallantr
1869 Toured northern Europe, western Russia, and Turkey with General Nathaniel Prentiss Banks As delegate of the Boston Board of Trade to the opening of the Suez canal, first met Count Ferdinand de Lesseps
1872 Bowles Brothers and Co., of which Appleton was a member, collapsed with serious injury to his personal fortune
1875 Delegate, conference of the association for the codification and reform of the law of nations, Hague, Netherlands
1877 Published Centennial Movement, 1876: A comedy in Five Acts. Boston: Lockwood, Brooks President, Free Trade Conference, Saratoga, N.Y.
1878 Delegate, International Congress for the Unification of Weights, Measures, and Coinage, Paris, France
1879 Delegate, Interfic Canal Congress, Paris, France Elected president, United States Board of Trade
1880 Interpreter for Count Ferdinand de Lesseps on his tour of the United States
1881-1888 American agent, Panama Canal Co.
1895 Traveled throughout Latin America
1887 Married Jeannette Ovington (separated 1889; divorced 1906)
1896 Visited Hawaii
1899 Member, Board of Overseers, Harvard College, Cambridge, Mass.
1904 Published Russian Life and Society as Seen in 1866-'67 by Appleton and Longfellow. Boston: [Press of Murray and Emery]
1905 Assisted at the peace conference culminating in the Treaty of Portsmouth, Portsmouth, N.H.
1906, Aug. 25 Died, Boston, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Nathan Appleton (1843-1906) span the period 1850-1904, with the bulk concentrated in the years 1876-1902. The collection consists largely of an autobiography, letters, newspaper articles, and other printed matter mostly relating to Appleton's connections with French attempts to construct a Panamanian canal and to his support of free trade.
Nathan Appleton was born the son of a more noted Nathan (1779-1861), a merchant and congressman from Boston. After education at Harvard College, the younger Nathan served as an officer of volunteer artillerists in the federal armies. His wartime experiences impressed him deeply, forming a favorite subject for the speeches he was frequently asked to deliver throughout the rest of his life.
After touring Europe, Appleton met Count Ferdinand de Lesseps at the opening of the Suez canal in 1869. From that time, Appleton became devoted to both the count and his projects. The two parts of the manuscript "Recollections of Brevet Captain Nathan Appleton, U.S.V." ("Action and Counteraction" and "Dramatis Personae") among the writings in this collection tell of Appleton’s acquaintance with Count de Lesseps over thirty years, centering on his eight years of service as American agent for the French company that attempted to construct a sea-level canal across Panama. Also in the collection is a notebook in which Appleton memorialized his friend: "Souvenirs of Ferdinand de Lesseps, 1898-99."
Appleton's interest in the promotion of peaceful commerce between nations showed itself also in his action to establish free trade, culminating in his election in 1879 to the presidency of the United States Board of Trade. Letters and notes in the correspondence in this collection, addresses by Appleton and others among the writings, and printed matter among the miscellany treat the reduction or abolition of tariffs between nations.
Appleton's activities on behalf of the Panamanian canal and free trade, his frequent and worldwide travels, and his position as a member of a prominent Bostonian family are reflected in the printed matter and correspondence. Among the many correspondents represented in the collection are Edwin M. Bacon, George E. Balknap, Edward Bellamy, Henry Bergh, George B. Cortelyou, Andrew Gregg Curtin, John William Draper, John W. Forney, Marcus Alonzo Hanna, George Frisbie Hoar, John Davis Long, Charles Eliot Norton, John C. Spooner, and Anne Whitney.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material.
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm80057067
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - General, circa 1850-1902, undated (Box 1)
  - Letters and notes relating to free trade, 1877, undated (Box 1)
  - United States Board of Trade, 1878-1881 (Box 1)
  - Published letters, 1884-1904 (Box 1)
- Writings (Box 1)
  - Note and notebooks, circa 1870-1904 (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical notes, 1875-1890 (Box 1)
  - "Recollections of Brevet Captain Nathan Appleton, U.S.V.: 'Action and Counteraction,'" circa 1902 (Box 1)
    - pages I-VI, a-e, unnumbered, and 1-173 (Box 1)
    - pages 174-331 (Box 1)
    - pages 332-501 (Box 2)
    - pages 502-689 (Box 2)
    - pages 690-893 (Box 2)
  - "Recollections of Brevet Captain Nathan Appleton, U.S.V.: 'Dramatis Personae,'" circa 1902 (Box 2)
    - pages 894-1082 (Box 2)
    - pages 1083-1262 (Box 2)
    - pages 1263-1471 (Box 3)
    - pages 1472-1689 (Box 3)
    - pages 1690-1894 (Box 3)
  - Petition, 1876 (Box 3)
  - Addresses and tributes, 1876-circa 1904 (Box 3)
  - Appleton, William Sumner (cousin), compositions, 1854-1856 (Box 3)
  - Writings by others, 1876-circa 1877 (Box 3)
- Miscellany (Box 4)
  - Annotated photographs, circa 1870-1885 (Box 4)
  - Invitations, notices, and cards, 1877-1904, undated (Box 4)
  - Printed matter (Box 4)
    - Free trade, circa 1876-1877 (Box 4)
    - Panamanian canal, Panamanian canal, 1879-1904 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper and magazine articles, circa 1884-1891 (Box 4)
  - Passport and other printed matter, circa 1867-1899 (Box 4)